<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MlSense</title>
    <link>https://mlsense.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on MlSense</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 16:56:04 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mlsense.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://mlsense.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlsense.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a Data Scientist at Zeta Global building recommendation engines for media publishing houses. These days I am learning how recommendation engines work, exploring techniques like matrix factorization, factorization machines, and others. I have started using Python and I am loving it! I am a graduate from IIT Kharagpur with a Masters in Mathematics and Computing. I have picked up much of my understanding of machine learning at @WalmartLabs where I worked as Sr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Hugo Post</title>
      <link>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/my-first-hugo-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 16:56:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/my-first-hugo-post/</guid>
      <description> Hello world,
I am trying to create a site using Hugo static site generator. This is a markdown page.
Trying color syntaxing using pygmentize import numpy as np import pandas as pd import matplotlip.pyplot as plt import seaborn as sns # Add comment here  Using hugo syntax highlight import numpy as np import pandas as pd import matplotlip.pyplot as plt import seaborn as sns </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time series and forecasting using R</title>
      <link>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/time-series-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/time-series-post/</guid>
      <description>Time series forecasting is a skill that few people claim to know. Machine learning is cool. And there are a lot of people interested in becoming a machine learning expert. But forecasting is something that is a little domain specific. Retailers like Walmart, Target use forecasting systems and tools to replenish their products in the stores. An excellent forecast system helps in winning the other pipelines of the supply chain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Types of data in recommender systems</title>
      <link>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/types_of_data_recommender_system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/types_of_data_recommender_system/</guid>
      <description>There are two ways in which we can collect data for building recommender systems — explicit and implicit. In this post, we will talk about both types of data, their characteristics and the challenges with them. Explicit feedback datasets The dictionary meaning of explicit is to state clearly and in detail. Explicit feedback data as the name suggests is an exact number given by a user to a product. Some of the examples of explicit feedback are ratings of movies by users on Netflix, ratings of products by users on Amazon.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>