<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>recommendation system on MlQuest</title>
    <link>https://mlsense.github.io/tags/recommendation-system/</link>
    <description>Recent content in recommendation system on MlQuest</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mlsense.github.io/tags/recommendation-system/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Amazon&#39;s item-item Collaborative filtering recommendation algorithm [paper summary]</title>
      <link>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/2019-06-02/item_item_recs_paper_summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/2019-06-02/item_item_recs_paper_summary/</guid>
      <description>This paper published in 2003 by Amazon explains how their basic recommendation algorithm works and is one of the papers that anyone interested in recommendation systems should give a read. I have been working in RS (recommender systems) domain at my present company for the last two years. Since the paper is dated almost fifteen years back, the algorithm may sound basic to you but it still works today. The paper starts with talking about the different class of techniques we have for RS and why they do not work for Amazon and then it finally talks about their item-to-item collaborative filtering algorithm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Types of data in recommender systems</title>
      <link>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/types_of_data_recommender_system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlsense.github.io/posts/types_of_data_recommender_system/</guid>
      <description>There are two ways in which we can collect data for building recommender systems — explicit and implicit. In this post, we will talk about both types of data, their characteristics and the challenges with them. Explicit feedback datasets The dictionary meaning of explicit is to state clearly and in detail. Explicit feedback data as the name suggests is an exact number given by a user to a product. Some of the examples of explicit feedback are ratings of movies by users on Netflix, ratings of products by users on Amazon.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>